<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>dapo</title>
    <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on dapo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 21:52:25 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://d-dorazio.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Generating terrain mesh from noise functions</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/terrain-mesh-from-noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 21:52:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/terrain-mesh-from-noise/</guid>
      <description>Recently at work we bought a 3d printer and sure enought I wanted something cool to print to try out the new toy. I didn&#39;t want to just search for ready to print models online because that didn&#39;t sound fun. Instead, I figured I should print something that I created.
Since I don&#39;t know how to use 3d modeling software (e.g. Blender) to create good looking models, my only option left was to build a program able to generate them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buzz, the ray tracer!</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/buzz/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 22:29:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/buzz/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&#39;ve been working on a toy ray tracer to learn a bit about how 3D renderers work. I also took the opportunity to learn a little bit of math and a whole ton about computer graphics in general. This post isn&#39;t a tutorial on how to build a ray tracer because there&#39;s a ton of resources online already; it is mostly the journey I went through when writing Buzz, my toy ray tracer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JV</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/jv/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 10:35:15 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/jv/</guid>
      <description>JSON is a really common format and I think it works well 90% of the time. However, it&#39;s not perfect and it lacks some features that would be handy sometimes.
In particular, it doesn&#39;t have a way to specify a reference to a value in the document. A common solution is to store the id of the referenced object, but it&#39;s not always possible (or convenient) to do so.
Anyway, it&#39;s trivial to come up with a custom string format that represents a path to a value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chip8 emulator in Rust!</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/chip8-emulator-rs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 22:31:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/chip8-emulator-rs/</guid>
      <description>Some coworkers of mine are really into game development and emulators in particular. In fact, these days they&#39;re building emulators for the Playstation 1 and the Game Boy! I decided to write an emulator too just for fun. However, I didn&#39;t want to implement such complex consoles, but I wanted to start off with a simpler platform first. According to the internet the simplest emulator you can build is a Chip8 emulator so I went for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Category Theory</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/category-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 13:39:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/category-theory/</guid>
      <description>During the holiday season I finally decided to learn something about Category theory because it seems to be the hot topic in the Haskell community. The book I used to guide me in this journey is Category theory for programmers by Bartosz Milewski.
I cannot say I fully understood it, I&#39;m far away from doing so, but I want to write down what I think I learned nonetheless. I hope this will clarify my thoughts and maybe help someone else.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terminal graphics with Braille characters</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/terminal-graphics-braille/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2018 21:21:53 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/terminal-graphics-braille/</guid>
      <description>At work, I&#39;m currently developing a 3D web CAD for modeling shoes which is a really interesting project, but also very challenging! Since writing geometric code is really tricky, we spend a lot of time writing tests and making sure the code is well documented. However, documentation is made up by text for the most part, but sometimes a drawing is way more useful than a lot of words. For example, try to explain what perpendicular and parallel mean without drawing anything.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use Property based testing whenever you can!</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/property-based-testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 23:03:31 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/property-based-testing/</guid>
      <description>Recently I had to implement some geometric data structures and algorithms in Rust so that I could use them in matto. In particular, I built a simple K-d tree, an algorithm to find the convex hull, the K-means clustering algorithm and a couple of polygon related utilities. Building such things is relatively easy for the most part, but the corner cases are really tricky to handle properly. In this post I&#39;d like to show how I used property based testing to even recognize those corner cases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Take on Documenting Code and Readability</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/my-take-on-documenting-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 12:08:32 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/my-take-on-documenting-code/</guid>
      <description>Recently we had a workshop at my workplace about how to document code. Unfortunately I wasn&#39;t able to attend it, but the topic was in the air in the following days and I chatted about it a few times with my colleagues. I thought this was a solved problem because a lot of ink has already been spilled on it, but after a lot of discussions it became clear to me that it is not the case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Turing Machine</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/functional-turing-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 21:30:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/functional-turing-machine/</guid>
      <description>A week ago or so I managed to complete the Advent of Code 2017 and it was a really fun experience. Most of the problems was really interesting(the spiral memory is probably my favorite), but the problem for day 25 especially attracted me. Basically it was about implementing a Turing Machine.
This is not rocket science since a Turing Machine is a simple idea(like all the brilliant ideas) and a lot of ink has been spilled on it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Resolutions</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/2018-resolutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 23:22:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/2018-resolutions/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve just finished watching Interstellar for probably the 7th time since it came out and I really enjoy it every time. The soundtrack is amazing and it adds a completely new dimension to the movie. The plot is literally mind blowing, but I know that a lot of people don&#39;t get it. I don&#39;t care, I understand the amount of pieces I need to find it interesting and that&#39;s enough for me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signals from the past</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/signals-from-the-past/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 01:30:06 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/signals-from-the-past/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s just common knowledge that pressing Ctrl-C will usually terminate a long running command in a shell. How cool is that? But, how does it work?
Every developer that has done some little system programming on Linux knows that the answer is signals. They are defined in the POSIX standard and are a (very) limited form of inter-process communication. The idea is really simple: a signal is sent to a program to notify it that an event has occurred.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a developer working at develer where I can build a lot of cool stuff working with great people. Currently I&#39;m working on a 3D CAD for fashion shoes that runs in the browser!
My interests are functional programming and programming language design.
This blog will collect my ramblings about whatever I find interesting or worth to be written down.
If you wish to reach out to me, you can find me on twitter and github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Library</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/library/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/library/</guid>
      <description>Just a collection of random thoughts about books and papers that I read or that I&#39;m reading.
Category theory for programmers I read this book as an introduction to category theory which was intriguing me for a long time. Even though it explicitly says &amp;ldquo;for programmers&amp;rdquo; I think it was still too math-y for me and it&#39;s a bit light on programming. Anyway, it was an enjoyable read and I was able to understand a lot of the math concepts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>