<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vogon&#39;s Ship</title>
    <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Vogon&#39;s Ship</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 21:30:52 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://d-dorazio.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Turing Machine</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/functional-turing-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 21:30:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/functional-turing-machine/</guid>
      <description>A week ago or so I managed to complete the Advent of Code 2017 and it was a really fun experience. Most of the problems was really interesting(the spiral memory is probably my favourite), but the problem for day 25 especially attracted me. Basically it was about implementing a Turing Machine.
This is not rocket science since a Turing Machine is a simple idea(like all the brilliant ideas) and a lot of ink has been spilled on it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Resolutions</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/2018-resolutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 23:22:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/2018-resolutions/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve just finished watching Interstellar for probably the 7th time since it came out and I really enjoy it every time. The soundtrack is amazing and it adds a completely new dimension to the movie. The plot is literally mind blowing, but I know that a lot of people don&amp;rsquo;t get it. I don&amp;rsquo;t care, I understand the amount of pieces I need to find it interesting and that&amp;rsquo;s enough for me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 22:20:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a developer working at develer where I can build a lot of cool stuff working with great people. My main interests are functional programming and programming language design. In my spare time I like solving twisty puzzles like the megaminx, but my favourite one is the plain old Rubik&amp;rsquo;s cube of course. I am not fast by any means though 😅 but I enjoy the experience a lot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signals from the past</title>
      <link>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/signals-from-the-past/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 01:30:06 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://d-dorazio.github.io/post/signals-from-the-past/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s just common knowledge that pressing Ctrl-C will usually terminate a long running command in a shell. How cool is that? But, how does it work?
Every developer that has done some little system programming on Linux knows that the answer is signals. They are defined in the POSIX standard and are a (very) limited form of inter-process communication. The idea is really simple: a signal is sent to a program to notify it that an event has occured.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>